<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Certain seasonable considerations and reasons humbly offered against reviving the act intituled, An Act for the Better Propagation and Preaching of the Gospel in Wales ... presented to the supreme authoritie the Parliament of the Common-wealth of England : with wholesome proposalls, touching the future disposall of the powers given by the said act.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 20 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A31524</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1754</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36296</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15633194</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15633194</idno>
            <idno type="VID">104269</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A31524)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104269)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1183:31)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Certain seasonable considerations and reasons humbly offered against reviving the act intituled, An Act for the Better Propagation and Preaching of the Gospel in Wales ... presented to the supreme authoritie the Parliament of the Common-wealth of England : with wholesome proposalls, touching the future disposall of the powers given by the said act.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Date of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church and state --  England.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  Wales.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:104269:1"/>
            <head>Certain ſeaſonable CONSIDERATIONS AND REASONS HUMBLY OFFERED, AGAINST Reviving the Act, Intituled, <hi>An Act for the better Propagation and Preaching of the Goſpel in</hi> Wales, <hi>and redreſſe of ſome Grievance there.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">Preſented to the Supreme Authoritie the Parliament of the Common-wealth of <hi>ENGLAND.</hi> WITH Wholeſome PROPOSALLS, touching the future diſpoſall of the powers given by the ſaid ACT.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Act veſteth in the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionere named in that Act, a double power,
<list>
                  <item>1. Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick.</item>
                  <item>2. Civill.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eccleſiaſtick; To amove from, and confer Eccleſiaſtical promotions, &amp;c. and to dispoſe of the Church Revenue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Obſervation.
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Wales</hi> having been many ages ſithence happily incorpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with <hi>England,</hi> and governed by the ſame Laws, as well thoſe of the Church, as Civill, by this Act are governed by diſtinct
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:104269:2"/>Laws, which in this conjunction of time may not give that pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique ſatisfaction.</item>
                  <item>
                     <p>2. If this Act is for the <hi>better Propagation of the Gospell in</hi> Wales, than the generall Act for all <hi>England</hi> is, it muſt be either becauſe of the matter of this Act, or the manner of proceedings thereupon, or ſome other peculiar Circumſtances.</p>
                     <p>The matter thereof is, <hi>To amove from, and confer Eccleſiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call promotions,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. The very ſame matter is veſted in the honourable Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee for Plundered Miniſters at <hi>Westminſter,</hi> for the diſpoſall of promotions in <hi>England;</hi> and the perſons of that Committee are all Members of Parliament. The greateſt part of the Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners in the aforeſaid Act for <hi>Wales,</hi> yea, all that meet to act by virtue thereof, except two perſons, are not members of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and in regard of their ſeverall relations and Intereſts, if not Judgements, are the rather ſubject to partialities.</item>
                  <item>4. Neither is their meeting in <hi>Wales</hi> a leſſening of Charge; their meeting in <hi>Southwales</hi> being at <hi>Swanzey,</hi> in <hi>Northw<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>les</hi> at <hi>Wrexam,</hi> 70 miles diſtant from the perſons that are many times ſummoned to attend them; The Committee for Plunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Miniſters being far more certain, and quicker for their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patches, and more moderate for Fees allowed to their Officers.</item>
                  <item>5. It is unuſuall in the Engliſh Government to make Natives Iudges in their own Counties, &amp; (under favour) at this time moſt unſeaſonable, the late differences having rendred Neighbors and Countreymen leſſe affectionate to each other than former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſuch power may occaſion private vindication more than diſcharging publique Truſt, eſpecially (as it is obſerved) in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the <hi>Welſh</hi> Nation, ſo impower'd.</item>
                  <item>6. The Commiſſioners named in the ſaid Act are to act in any part of <hi>Southwales</hi> &amp; <hi>Northwales,</hi> ſo, that it iss poſſible that thoſe Commiſſioners living in the remoteſt place of <hi>Southwales</hi> may ſummon perſons living in the remoteſt parts of <hi>Northwales,</hi> and ſo thoſe of <hi>Northwales</hi> the Inhabitants of <hi>Southwales.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>7. The perſons of <hi>Southwales</hi> nominated Commiſſioners in the ſaid Act, are for the moſt part from two Counties, (1) <hi>Breck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nock, Caermarthen, Pembrook</hi> and <hi>Cardigan</hi> having but 5 Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners inhabiting in them.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The manner of proceeding directed by the Act is
<list>
                  <item>1. That 5 Commiſſioners may examine and eject, &amp;c.</item>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:104269:2"/>
                  <item> 2. That 12 (upon the Ejecteds complaints) might review, and determine.</item>
                  <item>3. That 12 (upon the Ejecteds appeal) are to transfer, and certifie the proceedings to the Committee for plundred Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>It is humbly obſerved,
<list>
                  <item>1. That 12 did very rarely meet, the time and place of mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting not uſually publiſhed, nor generally known, the propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gators living very remote one from another, and the Itine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants reſidence appointed for approvers altogether uncertain, one while in one Country, another while in another Country, and in no place certain.</item>
                  <item>2. If they meet, it is probable that the ſame 12 that adjud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged a Cauſe, would not transfer and certifie againſt their own Iudgements: And in caſe of refuſall there is no proviſion in the Act to inforce them, and during the three years time this Act continued, notwithſtanding the many hundreds that were ejected, we find few or any cauſe upon an appeal (though im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunately deſired) certified by the Commiſſioners.</item>
                  <item>3. In Caſe the Commiſſioners did transfer and certifie the proceedings before them to the Committee for plundred Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; yet the Act diſabled the Appellant to examine any more witneſſes; and it is poſſible, that, the depoſitions ſo trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd and certified were not laid down and certified according to the Examinants intentions, many, if not moſt of the perſons examined againſt ejected Miniſters, being illiterate men, ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of the Engliſh tongue, whereof many do complain, and thereby may be uncapable to make their juſt defence: and if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny did appeal whether the remedy may prove worſe than the diſeaſe, conſidering how difficult it will be for a poor man (diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled of means to defray neceſſary charges incident thereto) to recall &amp; annihilate that ſentence or judgment given be it never ſo injurious, the very Fifts allowed the ejected Miniſters Wives by the Act of Parliament being either denied them or allowed according to the Sequeſtrators undervaluations, whereby they are ſo far diſabled of means to appeal that many of them are ready to periſh for want of bread.</item>
                  <item>4. That theſe triennial powers are of dangerous conſequence, if the perſons intruſted miſuſe, non-uſe, or abuſe their power, and thoſe ſeverall powers continuing for three years may prove
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:104269:3"/>a temptation for honeſt men to act contrary to their Principles: wherefore it hath been the wiſdome of Common-wealths to prevent thoſe inconveniences by changing their powers often, and not giving them too much power at once, or giving them but a ſhort time to act, the better to mind them that their power is not perpetuall, and that they muſt ſhortly give an accompt of their ſtewardſhips, for at the the third years end the oppreſſor may be ſo rich and powerful,<note place="margin">It is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred that theſe 3 <hi>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens od<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>um juvenile concilium, &amp; P<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crum,</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>threw the flouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of the Roman Empire.</note> and the oppreſſed ſo poor and unable, that the party injuring may eaſily ſuppreſs and ſilence the cry of the party injured, whereras Iudges have their Commiſſions but <hi>qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diuſe benè geſſerint</hi> or <hi>durante benè placito;</hi> the Councell of State continues but for a year without new election; and all Mayors, Sheriffs, &amp; Bayliffs, are annually choſen and appointed, and liable to give an accompt of their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions in the precedent year of their power, and it is likewiſe deſired to be conſidered that oppreſſion and the abuſe of pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers have been the great billowes of the ſeverall wars and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions not only in <hi>Wales</hi> but alſo in this whole nation.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Civill power by the ſaid Act veſted in the Commiſſioners is a Power</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>1 To be Arbitrators.</item>
                  <item>2 To be a Committee of Indempnity.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Arbitrators in theſe words, <hi>A power to inquire and redreſs high miſdemeanours, oppreſſions, and injuries, often eſcaping un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puniſhed, becauſe of remoteneſs from</hi> London, <hi>and want of means in the party Complaining to be redreſſed by due courſe of Law, and the perſons complayning, and Complayneds ſubmiſſion, under their Hands and Seals to determine the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is humbly obſerved,
<list>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Quicquid <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>gas pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gas &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpice finem ſapiens in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipit à ſine</note>1. That upon this power of inquiring and redreſſing, the party complained on, may by this power be compell'd to ſubmit, or not; if not, this power is for no other uſe than to occaſion expence of time and moneys, in attendance upon ſummons; and in caſe the Commiſſioners therein named, have no power to trie any matter by bill, indictment, information, or original writ, or by verdict, demurrer, or examination of Witneſſes on oath, or to force the performance of their Adwards; this pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er muſt needs prove uſeleſs, troubleſome, and chargeable; and that which can attain to no reaſonable end, the Law rejects as a thing inutile and uſeleſſe.</item>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:104269:3"/>
                  <item> 2. If the party complained upon may by this act be compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to ſubmit, then the Juſtices of Aſſize, and of Peace, offices are ſwallowed up by this power, and without verdict, cauſes always determinable by verdict are adjudged; which brigeth a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt betwixt the Judges and Juſtices power and the Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Vide</hi> the Lord <hi>Cooks</hi> Expoſition of the 29th Chapter of <hi>Magna Charta</hi> in his 2 part Inſti<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>utes fo. 51 con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding of <hi>Empſon</hi> and <hi>Dudley</hi> who were juſtly exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted for it.</note> their juriſdiction being not diſtinguiſhed, and ſuters thereby confounded, and lyable to unneceſſary charges and trouble; and by ſuch a power, an Arbitrary power of a Star-chamber might probably be exerciſed, judgments and decrees attained, and the antient way of tryalls by jury deſtroyed; the Commiſſioners (thoſe that act) being not bred in the Laws, and therefore not ſo competent to judge of Adwards, and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Lawes, as Judges are, neither are the Commiſſioners (as ludges be) upon their Oathes, in diſcharging this great truſt, for any thing appearing in the ſaid act; and by the Law all Arbitrators ought to be indifferently choſen: the perſons named in the ſaid Act were not choſen by the Countries, who were ignorant thereof untill the Act was publiſhed, moſt of the Counties having no Repreſentatives in Parliament to ſpeak for them at the paſſing thereof, who have ſince declared their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like of the execution thereof.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>It is obſerved,
<list>
                  <item>3 That <hi>remoteneſſe from London</hi> is not much more from any parts of <hi>Wales,</hi> than from ſome parts of <hi>Wales</hi> to thoſe places where the Commiſſioners meet, and the uncertainty and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frequency of their meetings, extraordinary delays and exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive fees, have given cauſe for many to believe that this courſe is the <hi>remoteſt</hi> and moſt chargeable way <hi>for redreſſing of grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>As to their power of Committee of Indempnity, it is likewiſe humbly obſerved,
<list>
                  <item>1 That the party Complayning, upon the Complayneds refuſall to ſubmit to the Commiſſioners <hi>Arbitration,</hi> may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive incouragement to implead the party Complayned before the Commiſſioners <hi>as Committee of Indempnity,</hi> who may as <hi>Committee of Indempnity</hi> (though not as <hi>Arbitrators</hi>) inforce ſubmiſſion and obedience. What hath happened there this three laſt years of that nature, is not proper to be here incerted, ſince the Act of Oblivion hath pardoned both the offences and offendors.</item>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:104269:4"/>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Qui facit per alium facit per ſe.</hi> And Act of Parliament that a man ſhall be Iudge in his own cauſe is a void Act.</note>2 The Act of Oblivion having ended moſt matters properly determinable by the Committee of Indempnity there, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of that power can prove for no other uſe, than to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>incourage litigious perſons to moleſt their neighbours; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed nothing is properly determinable before them but what muſt relate to thoſe that now act under them, by colour of their ſeverall powers, Military, Civill, and Eccleſiaſticall.</item>
                  <item>3 Thoſe of <hi>Southwales</hi> have the command of the Military power now on foot there; the power of Iuſtices of Peace, Commiſſioners for Propagation, for Arbitration, and Indemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; Commiſſioners of monthly Aſſeſſments, and of Seque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations of Papiſts and Delinquents Eſtates, and for the moſt part of very near kin and alliance to each other; Leſſors and Leſſees by their near friends and agents of the moſt and beſt Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtick Promotions and Sequeſtred Eſtates there, the power Civil, Martial, and Eccleſiaſtick, in the ſame perſons, ſubſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to one another, to the too haſty and viſible improvement of particular mens fortunes; and how theſe wayes of accumula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting all theſe powers in thirteen Counties, into the hands of a few particular perſons (upon any pretence whatſoever) are conſiſtent with the wiſdom and policie of a State, and the well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of <hi>Wales,</hi> is humbly left to your honours grave conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</item>
                  <item>4 It is worth the taking notice of, that thoſe perſons from <hi>Wales,</hi> that appear in ſoliciting the continuance of this Act, are (for the moſt part) either perſons formerly nominated in the ſaid Act, or <hi>Perners</hi> of the profit of the <hi>Eccleſiaſtick</hi> revenue, or having relation to thoſe that injoy the ſame. And it is hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly deſired, that the worthy Members of Parliament will take notice of the carriage of three of the itinerant Approbationers at the Parliament Door, Friday the 25 of <hi>March</hi> inſtant, to beg the renewing of the Act, and whether it better becomed them to be preaching the word in <hi>Wales,</hi> where there is a ſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of Preachers, than to ſpend their time in <hi>London,</hi> to ſollicit the continuance of their former power and advantage.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quaerie </seg>1</label> 
               <note place="margin">Touching the eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall powers.</note>It is humbly prayed it may be conſidered whether the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners named in the ſaid Act walk'd with ſuch rigidneſs in the ejecting of the former Miniſters, and Schoolmaſters, that ſmall offences of 10 or 20 years ſtanding were freſhly arreig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as Capital crimes and ſmall crimes unpardonable, without
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:104269:4"/>reſpects to their abilities, parts, and readineſs to conform, and become more ſerviceable for the future to the Church &amp; State under the preſent eſtabliſhed government, and whether humane prudence, if not Chriſtian Charity ſhould have induced them to continue the moſt able, conformable, and beſt qual<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fied of them, that never perſonally acted againſt the Parliament, at leaſt wiſe, untill they could provide better in their roomes, and not to leave the Country naked, and not above three or four to ſupply ſome Counties, and whether there be 700 pariſhes beſides Chappels of eaſe in <hi>Southwales,</hi> and above 600 of them unſupplied, to the famine of the word of God, and that many of the Itinerants, and Schoolmaſters, now employed and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to officiate, be not more ſcandalous than ſome of thoſe eje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, and ſome that bore arms againſt the Parliament, and a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt in the town of <hi>Brecknock</hi> that keeps ſchool, and whether Ieſuits and Seminary Prieſts were not diſcharged in <hi>Monmouth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> without being proceeded againſt according to the Law of the Land.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quaerie </seg>2</label> Whether the Commiſſioners for propagation make an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt but of 19000 l. or thereabouts, for the tithes &amp;c. in the ſaid 7 Counties for 2 years, and do by anſwer ſay the Fifts and contributions are not fully known nor allowed, and that they have not mony to pay the Miniſters approbationers, if ſo, what propagation or better ſupply the ſaid Counties are like to have for the future, if their power be renued, and how well they have diſpoſed of the tithes, whether or no the Petitioners offer 20000 l. for the tithes for one year which is more by 20000 l. then the Commiſſioners accompt for 2 years, as by the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars and reply of the Petitioners of the 6 Counties of <hi>South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wales</hi> and County of <hi>Monmouth</hi> lodged with the Honourable Committee of Plundred miniſters may more fully appear.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quaerie </seg>3</label> It is humbly deſired that the honourable Parliament will take notice, That the Commiſſioners anſwer was reported, before a Copie thereof granted the Petitioners; A particular Book of accompt of 60 ſheets of paper mentioned in the report, before a ſight and Copie thereof likewiſe granted, though the Petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners moved for it; An information againſt <hi>John Gunter</hi> repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted before he was ſummoned to anſwer the ſame, or had a Copie thereof. The particulars and Reply lodged by the Petitioners with the honorable Committee, (whereupon the Petitioners
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:104269:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>craved a Commiſſion to examine Witneſſes) left out of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, though once ordered to be reported; And this Report made before any one Witneſſe examined, or Commiſſion iſſued forth. And untill Commiſſions be iſſued forth, and Witneſſes examined, whereby matter of fact may appear, It is humbly leſe to your Honours conſideration, whether your Honours will think fit to continue the ſame powers on the ſame perſons, ſince their proceedings for the laſt 3 years have given ſo little ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to the Country and the State, in relation to the vaſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues there received.</p>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <head>Propoſalls humbly offered touching the future diſpoſall of the power given by the ſaid Act.</head>
                  <item>1. It is therefore humbly offered to your Honours grave Conſideration, whether or no it be not more of publique con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency, That the power Eccleſiaſtick given by the ſaid Act be veſted in the honourable Committee for Plundered Miniſters, the Lords Commiſſioner<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of the Great Seal of <hi>England</hi> for the time being, and Sir <hi>John Thorowgood,</hi> and other the Truſtees named in an Act of the 8th of <hi>June,</hi> 1649. Intituled, <hi>An Act for providing Maintentanance for Preaching Miniſters, and other piou<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> uſes,</hi> in the ſame manner as it is alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in <hi>England</hi> verſted upon the ſaid honourable perſons, being perſons of known integritie and honour, and not of ſuch perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal relations in <hi>Wales,</hi> with ſuch ſpeciall power and direction therein for the better carrying on and managing of ſo great and weighty a work, as to your Honours wiſdom ſhall ſeem meet.</item>
                  <item>2. That as to the power given by the ſaid Act to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners therein named to Act as Committee of Indempnity, for as much as the Parliament have by their ſeverall Acts of the 23. of <hi>June,</hi> and the 8. of <hi>October</hi> 1652. veſted the ſame in <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel Moyer</hi> Eſq; and other the Commiſsioners therein named, as well in <hi>England</hi> as in <hi>Wales;</hi> It is humbly left to conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whether the ſame power may not be ſtill continued in the ſaid perſons.</item>
                  <item>3. As to the power given by the ſaid Act for <hi>Arbitration,</hi> For as much as the Parliament have appointed Iudges, Iuſtices of Peace, and other Magiſtrates in <hi>Wales,</hi> and elſewhere, to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the Laws of the Land by ſafe and ſetled rules, intruſted in diſcreet perſons bred in the knowledge of the Law; It is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe left to conſideration, whether the ſame power may not ſtill continue in them, and no otherwiſe, in the ſame manner of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:104269:5"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
